A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Office Files of Karen L. McGuinness FA525
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Office Files of Karen L. McGuinness
1975-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA525
2.4 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Subject Files.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Developing Countries Program correspondence and subject files.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, >Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
- Chronological Files, 1985-1987; I
  - 1985, Telexes Re: Southeast Asia (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986, Letters, Sep 1985-Dec 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986, Memoranda (1 of 2), Jun 1985-Dec 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986, Memoranda (2 of 2), Jun 1985-Dec 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986, Telexes, Jan 1985-Dec 1986 (Box 1)
  - 1986, Telexes (Box 1)
  - 1986-1987, Telexes (incoming) (Box 1)
  - 1986-1987, Telexes (outgoing) (Box 1)
  - 1987, Letters, Jan-Nov 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1987, Memoranda, Jan-Nov 1987 (Box 1)
  - 1987, Telexes, Jan 1987-Nov 1987 (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1975-1988; II
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - ASEAN Law Association, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Asia Watch, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Asia Watch -- Fiscal Year 1987 Proposal Recommendation, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee (BRAC), 1985 (Box 1)
  - Child Survival, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS), 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chinese Visitors to Latin America and Caribbean, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Chinese Young Economists, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Consumer Unions, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Cultural Preservation, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Economic System Reform Delegation, 1986 (Box 2)
  - International Commission of Jurists, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - International Center for Research on Women, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - International Women's Health Coalition, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Islam, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Korea -- Human Rights, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Lawyer's Committee for Human Rights, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Lawasia Standing Committee for Human Rights, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - NRDC/CERC, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Social Sciences, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
  - Philippines Consultancy, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Group, 1981-1987 (Box 2)